Easy.
They're just getting rid of some ballast.
Back to work.
You'll get some butter tomorrow.
Thank you.
Hey, Kröger.
Hello, Tessa.
Hello.
Is that them?
The first ones.
There's another thousand
from Silesia and East Prussia.
Where are they going to live?
In the empty hotels.
There's two of them to every one of us.
What can you do?
The Russians are 50 km from Berlin.
At least it'll be the end
of Hitler's damn war.
Do they speak German?
They ARE German.
Hello there.
Hello...
Now the milk!
Too scared?
Don't you dare touch it.
Hello, Mother.
Hello, Aunt Ena.
Have you been working hard?
I've left the milk for the little ones
on the table.
What would we do without you, my son?
Tomorrow I'll get some butter.
Real butter?
Yes.
If we could only get some
white bread and honey too.
- Mother?
- Yes?
Is Hermann allowed in the parlor?
Why?
To borrow a book.
- Which one?
- Moby Dick.
As long as he doesn't get it dog-eared.
Go and get him.
Grandpa Arjan always says,
"Drink a lot and you get well drunk.
Read a lot and you get well read."
"Biological Betrayal".
My father wrote that.
Is this him?
BIOLOGICAL BETRAYAL -
PAST FACTS, FUTURE PREVENTION
- Your father wrote them all!
- Yes.
"The Hageners -
500 Years of Family History"
That was our house.
In Hamburg?
It burned down in the bombing.
Were you there when it burned down?
No, we were on our way to Amrum.
Here's the one you wanted.
He's called Hermann, like me.
No dog-ears!
You need to get more driftwood, Nanning.
Sure.
Will Father come home now?
- What makes you say that?
- Because the war's nearly over.
Who told you that?
I just heard.
- Who said it?
- Everyone knows that.
Was it Hermann?
No.
Maybe Grandpa Arjan said it to Hermann.
It wasn't Hermann.
I saw the refugees
arriving with Boy Kröger.
So Boy Kröger said it?
No.
One of the refugees?
Who then?
- Leave him alone.
- Stay out of it.
So, who said the war will be over soon?
Whoever it was is stabbing
our soldiers in the back.
You know why?
Our soldiers are fighting
for the Fatherland.
For us.
Lots of them are dying.
Or losing limbs, like Tewe the baker.
Now someone's saying the war is lost,
it was all in vain?
Is that what you want?
No.
These backstabbers
need to be severely punished.
So others will think twice
before doing the same.
Hille?
You understand?
Yes.
So...
it wasn't Boy Kröger,
it wasn't the refugees...
Hille! That's enough.
It was Tessa.
That loudmouth Tessa.
The tattletale...
Go and tell Local Group Leader Schneider
what Tessa said.
Keep the boy out of this.
- He has to learn to do his duty.
- Nanning...
You stay here and do your homework.
And you go to bed and rest.
- Hille!
- Let go of me.
First sit down.
Traitors.
Sorry Hille, I didn't mean to slap you.
Howdy, mainlander!
Howdy, Sam Gangsters!
What are you doing here in the prairie
in the middle of the night?
Looking for enemies.
And if you find any?
You know who gave you
that whaletooth knife?
What?
The knife. Who gave you it.
Uncle Theo.
Get lost, the school's full.
It's for Amrumers, not Polacks.
Chickenshits crapping their pants.
You're not an Amrumer either,
get over to them.
What...?
I'm as much an Amrumer as you.
And where are you from?
- None of your business.
- From Hamburg!
And your father?
Hamburg!
You can't even speak Öömrang.
Stay with the Polacks.
Richard's a moron.
He's got no idea.
Come, let's go in.
It doesn't matter where you were born,
it's who you're descended from.
Your bloodline.
These are my parents.
They got married in New York.
Your Uncle Onno was born there,
who now lives on Föhr.
But he's an Amrumer.
Look at those cars.
This is where I was born. On this ship.
On the way back to Amrum.
Yes, you were born in Hamburg,
but through me, your Amrumer blood
goes back nine generations.
You come from a family of whalers.
We're in your ancestors' house,
how could you not be an Amrumer?
Who are they?
Uncle Theo.
The one who gave me the knife?
Did I tell you that?
Sam Gangsters.
Stay away from him.
And who's the woman?
Mom's coming, pumpkin.
Put it back.
Hey, pumpkin.
Let's go to the kitchen.
I'm a ninth-generation Amrumer!
Who cares?
Let's go.
Come on.
That's it, push!
You'll get extra if you manage this.
Push!
Mrs. Bendixen, you've been
undermining military morale
in front of two Hitler Youth Jungvolk.
Are they Jungvolk members?
Hille Hagener's son is.
You should know.
You're aware of the punishment
for undermining military morale?
No.
You think you're untouchable
because I need your potatoes
for the island.
But some of the refugees are farmers,
so I'll replace you.
And you'll be up in court.
That's what's going to happen.
I made sure of it.
Enjoy your day.
Nanning?
Take your things.
And clear off.
I don't want any rats around here.
Get out of here!
The apple doesn't fall far from the tree!
No butter?
Tessa sent you packing.
Go fetch water, please.
Cannons instead of butter.
We can't spread cannons on our bread.
Tessa's isn't the only farm on Amrum.
No one wants your boy
on their farm anymore.
There's still plenty
of upstanding farmers.
But none of them wants a snitch.
It is being reported
from the Führer Headquarters...
Turn it up.
that this afternoon,
our Führer, Adolf Hitler,
at his command post
in the Reich Chancellery,
fighting Bolshevism
to his very last breath,
has fallen for Germany.
On April 30, the Führer...
I've got you.
Hille, come.
Nanning! The baby's coming,
let's get her in the bedroom.
You're okay, I've got you.
Everything's okay.
On the bed.
Get the kids out!
Go.
Close the door!
The German people bow their heads
in the deepest grief and reverence.
Let her cry.
It'll strengthen her lungs.
Nanning?
Could you please take the bread out?
It's disgusting.
You could eat it later.
All I want is white bread
with butter and honey.
BAKERY
Morning, Nanning.
Uncle Tewe, do you only have rye bread?
And dark rye bread.
Is there no white bread on Amrum anymore?
There's no wheat.
They apparently need wheat flour
to stem the soldiers' bleeding.
So it's medicine?
It didn't help with my arm.
I can give you
something for her appetite.
She wants to eat.
But only white bread
with butter and honey.
That'll be tricky.
You might have to trade one of your hens.
The hens belong to the pastor.
We just get eggs for feeding them.
Could you give me some wheat flour?
What makes you think
I might have wheat flour?
Because it's medicine.
That's what I heard.
Just a moment.
Here you go. Medicine.
Not bad, my boy!
Can you wait a bit
before you start baking?
I need to get honey and butter first.
Could you get some eggs too?
You don't need eggs to make bread.
You do to make cakes.
If you get me some eggs,
I'll bake your bread.
But it's gonna be a small one.
As long as it's white.
- What do you have there?
- Nothing.
Nothing?
They're for Tewe.
- What do you get in return?
- White bread for Mother.
Nonsense. Give me the eggs.
They'll be our last ones
now we get no more feed.
And don't take my bike without asking.
Or you'll be in real trouble.
Did Mother eat today?
She's stubborn as a mule.
- Morning.
Why weren't you at school yesterday?
I had to get food.
I could've helped you.
You help Tessa.
- Where are you going?
- To the geese.
We could do that together after school.
Go away, shoo.
Get lost.
Go away.
See?
No honey.
But I need honey.
Which part of "no honey"
don't you understand?
It's for a Party member.
Look here.
I use sugar water to make honey
until the heather comes into bloom.
Can't you make me some with this?
It's all I have left.
Is there no sugar on Amrum anymore?
The wretched English
have control of the North Sea.
The mudflats too?
I've never seen a tank on the mudflats.
Why aren't you in school?
I went to see Hedi Storm.
Why?
For Mother's bread and honey.
She doesn't need bread and honey,
what she needs is meat.
She said she finds food disgusting.
- Apart from bread and honey.
- Nonsense.
If you're not in school,
go get us a rabbit.
Go on.
Or I'll tell your mother
you're not in school.
Back from school already?
No school.
Hinrichs isn't coming anymore.
Is he sick?
No one knows.
- Can you show me how to catch rabbits?
- Sure, wait here.
Hermann?
Do you have any butter?
All gone.
Have you started Moby Dick?
I find it hard to understand.
So did I.
Did you read it all?
Aunt Ena read most of it to me.
Grandpa Arjan reads to me too.
Does he like it?
He says Captain Ahab is like Hitler.
- But don't rat on me to your mother.
- I didn't rat on Tessa!
My mother worked it out herself.
What did Grandpa Arjan mean
when he said Ahab is like Hitler?
Captain Ahab is like Hitler
and the ship...
- What's it called again?
- The Pequod.
The Pequod is Germany,
and it sinks because of Ahab.
So who's Moby Dick?
- The Americans.
- Or the Russians.
Churchill.
Maybe Moby Dick is supposed to be God.
A stock pigeon!
They nest in rabbit holes.
I bet we'll find one.
Grab it by its hind legs.
Your turn.
Go on.
Mainlander.
Harder!
Hello, Grandpa.
Hello, boys.
Grandpa Arjan?
Can you gut a rabbit for me?
Do it yourself.
I don't know how.
Can you teach me?
Can't you see?
I'm busy printing money.
Grandpa Arjan always says
that smoked flatfish is like Amrum-money.
Make yourself useful.
His mother needs meat.
But don't puke all over my barn.
What do I do?
Stick your knife in here,
and cut straight down.
But keep it vertical,
you don't want to pierce the guts.
We'd better leave it then.
More force.
Keep the knife vertical.
Cut through the rib cage.
It's just cartilage.
Open it up.
Out with the gooey bits.
Good.
Congratulations.
Go wash your hands.
Not bad, right?
For a mainlander.
Is this a radio?
There's no radio here.
If I tell you something,
can you keep it to yourself?
- I can.
- No, Grandpa.
He's a Hitler Youth Jungvolk.
It's a radio, but not for communicating.
You can pick up more
than with standard-issue radios.
Even enemy stations?
Why did your grandpa go to New York?
Because he wanted to earn dollars?
He had to, Nanning.
We all went.
Sam Gangsters,
your Uncle Theo,
myself,
our sons.
When I'm grown up,
I'm going to New York too.
My son Deik is in the U.S. Army.
I need to know he's okay.
That's why I have the radio.
Let me raise a glass to Nanning,
our champion hunter.
And to me!
You too, you cheeky thing.
Go on then, eat up.
You too, Nanning.
It's not every day
we have rabbit for dinner.
Eat something, Hille.
Your baby needs milk.
What kind of a world is this
for a child to grow up in?
Destruction.
It's all you know.
Because you're consumed by envy,
because no man wants you.
Because you're a nihilist with no values.
Go.
Pack your things and never come back.
If you don't want to see me, you go.
The house is half mine.
Oh! Nanning.
Could you spare some sugar
and butter, Uncle Onno?
Well...
Come in.
How's your mother?
She won't eat anything
since the Führer died.
Only white bread with butter and honey.
Let's see.
I'm out of butter.
Until tomorrow.
How about sugar?
Sugar.
Just a little.
Recite the mottoes
of the Hitler Youth Jungvolk.
Jungvolk are strong...
But Hitler's dead.
Here, he lives on.
So...
Jungvolk are strong...
Uncle Onno, I need to get back
before the tide comes in.
Then there's no sugar.
Jungvolk are strong,
obedient and true.
Jungvolk are comrades.
To the Jungvolk, honor is everything.
Thank you.
Say hello to your mother.
You're soaking wet!
Where were you?
I went to Uncle Onno's.
All the way to Föhr and back?
I got sugar. I'm going to trade it
for honey for Mother.
Where's my bike?
I lost it in the mudflats
when the tide came in.
Are you mad?
There's quicksand in those tidal creeks.
Do you want your mother to die of grief?
Now get out of those clothes.
Don't go indoors
with that filthy uniform.
- What do you want?
- To work for you again.
- Go away!
- Thank you, my boy.
I didn't rat on you.
So how did your mother
get that in her head?
I just asked if my father
would be coming home.
Because the war will soon be over.
Did you get the summons?
What summons?
From Local Group Leader Schneider.
They have other worries right now.
I have them now.
Will you sell me some butter?
Do you even have money?
Amrum-money.
We could use some of that.
Go on then.
Howdy, Sam Gangsters.
Howdy.
Can I help you?
Fetch me some more flatfish.
Can you spare some smoked ones?
Are you buying?
No.
I want to work for them.
- Are you afraid?
- Of what?
The sea.
You're not afraid of the sea either.
I am.
- Do the seal for me.
- What?
Keep going.
What is that rifle?
A Winchester.
What's a Winchester?
Back when I was a cowboy,
I shot buffalo with it.
Why didn't you stay in America?
Because of Black Friday.
The day when all Americans wanted
to withdraw their money from the banks.
The money ran out.
Panic everywhere.
People jumping out of windows.
No money meant
they couldn't afford steaks.
It was every man for himself.
But lots of Amrumers stayed in America.
There are more Amrumers in New York
than here, did you know?
What about Uncle Theo?
There was this woman in Hamburg.
Ruth Danziger.
He was in love with her.
We all were.
But his limericks made her laugh,
she only had eyes for him.
What are limericks?
An Amrumer, thick as a brick
Bragged about his mighty big dick
A drunken old bird
looked over and slurred:
"You angel!
Come over here quick!"
That's a limerick.
Ruth and Theo wanted to get married.
But it was forbidden.
Why?
Exactly.
They wanted to emigrate.
But they weren't allowed to.
Let me tell you something.
Your mother is Theo's cousin.
She could've helped them out.
Because your dad's a Nazi big shot.
But they didn't.
You go and ask her why not.
Theo was out on a whaling boat.
When the war broke out,
he couldn't return.
Now he's in America.
What happened to Ruth?
Ruth Danziger
was taken away by the Nazis
and sent to a concentration camp.
The Nazis killed her.
Thanks.
You're lying.
That's how it was.
My parents didn't do that.
Hey, what's that?
Give it here!
Uncle Theo!
Can you tell me another limerick?
You had just been born
when I gave that to your mother.
Do you want it back?
What my parents did isn't my fault.
No, it's not,
but you're still connected to it.
Like it or not, when I see you
I'm reminded of your parents.
Nanning?
Can't you sleep?
Come here.
Uncle Onno?
Oskar!
Help!
Why don't you help him?
Oskar!
He can't swim. Do something!
Please!
Hold on to it, Oskar!
What would I have told Mother?
The tide's coming in.
- It really is tiny.
- Told you so.
- Why the flower?
- Because the war's over.
What?
The war is over.
Germany surrendered.
- To freedom!
To freedom!
Come join us!
Come on.
Mother?
Look.
White bread with butter and honey.
Just put it in the kitchen.
But Mother...
Put it in the kitchen.
Get a hold of yourself, Nanning.
Stop crying.
Stop crying!
Nanning...
We lost the war
because of cry-babies like you.
Do you realize?
Get a hold of yourself.
Get a hold of yourself!
Get a hold of yourself, okay?
Stop crying.
Stop it!
Nanning, stop it.
Be a man!
Good.
Come on.
That's better.
Now go get the bread.
You pig!
- You greedy pig!
- Mother!
Nanning!
What's gotten into you? Stop!
- Leave me alone!
- Enough.
Have you gone mad?
I was hungry!
J. QUEDENS
BUTCHER'S
Come.
Morning.
- Hello, Jens.
- Hille.
- Hello, boys.
- Hello.
What can I get for these?
Nothing anymore.
That's over.
How do people pay now then?
With dollars.
Or English pounds.
Or they trade.
We're not farmers,
we don't have anything to trade.
You have relatives in New York.
Get them to send you some.
Wait outside, please.
Macker, you too. Macker!
Come on.
Can't I get something on credit?
I can't make a living like that.
Just this once?
If I do it for you,
they'll all be asking.
I won't tell anyone.
I'm needed in the back.
Come back with dollars.
Then you'll get something.
Let's go, children.
- Hille!
- Don't turn around.
Stop!
Keep walking.
- What do you think you're doing?
- Hands off my mother.
Give it back.
Come, children.
- Let go of me!
- Let go of my mother!
Give it back
or I'll call the military police.
Now get out of here.
Dear Hille,
I really admire how you've coped
these last few months on the island.
I'm doing fine
given the circumstances.
Daily life at the camp is monotonous.
But the provisions are adequate.
Sometimes we even get meat for lunch.
So please don't worry about me.
We're treated decently here.
The English even let us read
the permitted newspapers.
That's how I found out that the old
school system is being reinstated.
Attending an academic high school
will again be an entry requirement
for university in Hamburg.
I strongly urge you
to send Nanning to one.
It fills me with joy to read
that our children have
a healthy attitude towards the world.
I am particularly looking forward
to seeing Nanning.
Affectionately yours, Wilhelm.
Nanning!
- Are you done with it?
- Not even half, but here you go.
Keep it.
You're giving it to me?
What about your mother?
Doesn't matter.
Then maybe you'll think about me.
Thanks.
When you come back in the summer,
I'll have read it.
We're selling the house.
Selling it?
And I thought I was an Amrumer.
You're more an Amrumer than I am.
Grandpa Arjan always says,
"True Amrumers always leave eventually."
Nanning.
Nanning, come.
Get a move on, Hille!
We don't want you to miss your boat.
Don't worry. We'll be back.
Wait.
Wait!
Stop!
Kröger, stop.
Let's go.
NO ANIMALS WERE HARMED
DURING THE MAKING OF THIS MOVIE.